yeah so what we were talking about just
before we started recording was just
notion that the c19 is implicating
perhaps all of the meta-crisis certainly
from my point of view since I spent most
of my time looking at it from the point
of view of the systemic side of it you
know I can say with confidence that's
implicating all the different aspects
the systemic side I think it's also
enacting I mean Chris and I were talking
about this Chris master Pietro Anaya
it's also sort of triggering aspects of
the meaning crisis in powerful ways for
people to make sense
yo I'm interested in learning in this
conversation what's happening like how
the how that shadows up and even what
the flow back back through is because I
think it's crucial to grasp that it's
funny I do actually keep seeing the
right and left hemispheres I don't hope
that's useful so what we had talked
about was I'm right now doing work on
trying to put together or formulate a
form of decentralized collective
intelligence distributed cognition
appropriate to the scope and by the way
pace of this particular phenomenon
yeah I think keeping both of those in
mind is important scope and poise yes
yeah so to kind of our are not to
recapitulate but to capitulate what what
I'm seeing on my end is a first order is
that there's a bunch of different
systems that are clearly implicated in
each other so for example the primary
system in c19 is obviously at the
medical level a specific organism that
has specific characteristics in
relationships with the human organism
mm-hmm
and then of course it has its own
characteristics interior to itself so
what what is mutation we might look like
what it's a molecular structure is that
gives rise to the key characteristics of
how long it stays viable on surface all
that stuff right you got that at the
concrete level and you have the
relationship between the virus and any
human being and when you when you look
at that
that particular dynamic what you have is
a cloud of possibilities that that have
different weightings sure though you
have increasing data coming in so right
now we're net we're in a high
uncertainty phase much less than we were
a month ago but still high uncertainty
around there's terms that have now
become commonplace things like
the infection rate or the doubling rate
or the r0 you know and mortality or you
know case implications and impacts on
different characteristics the
relationship between the virus and
different human characteristic and then
we have already begun the process of
looking at from the point of view of
systemic impacts and so it's now pretty
pretty evident sorry I'm a backup so
going forward from this point forward
obviously we're walking in a place of
epistemological uncertainty so what I
will tend to do is I will take a
particular set of hypotheses which looks
to visual to me looks like a tunnel and
it has a certain diameter based upon its
probability and I'll walk down that
hypothesis as if that is reality
but but then I can back all the way back
out and shift and walk down another one
sure sure
and of course you can always do a depth
first versus breadth first so once one
purchase might be to start mapping out a
whole bunch of different tunnels so
you've got a sense of what the landscape
looks like another approaches to drill
down a baton so you get a sense of how
your thought process needs to inquire
into how you're in crew has to it has to
evolve as you actually discover more
detail and nuance and run particular
tunnel so one of the characteristics
that I think started getting a lot of
investigation
it started showing that more broadly in
the collective sense making no last week
was the relationship between the
robustness of a medical system and both
the virality and impact of the virus so
for example in Korea
where the medical system has a very high
robustness around testing there they can
and are choosing to test significantly
this is tending to show up as a
reduction in the viral viral expansion
because they've been a very good job of
identifying who in fact is carrying what
at what level and therefore able to do a
better job of a more precise and more
effective quarantine this it appears to
the kids equally if you take a look at
what happened in the distinction between
the impact of the mortality rates as a
proxy for impact between our array and
other Chinese regions the overwhelm of
the medical system the overwhelm of
doctors and nurses getting exhausted and
or sick the other one with hospital beds
being filled they remember equipment
being depleted Angeles Lee used is seems
to be deeply related to the differential
and impact and so once you hit a if you
if you sort of say there's a human human
beings without any capacity for medical
intervention it looks like you're
looking at maybe a five percent
mortality rate and by the way the
variance on where I just said is quite
why it may be much higher than that by
the way humans just natural in nature
and then as you apply medical
intervention you can drop that all the
way down into what looks like about 0.1
2.17
what that means is that the variance
between those two is going to be the
degree to which the medical system is
resilient or robust V the V the caseload
that it has to care so if you've got a
hundred patients and you can handle 300
then you would expect and you've got a
medical first world medical system you
would expect to see the total impact be
closer to point one seven and maybe
lower if you've got ten thousand
patients can handle two hundred you
might say the total mortality rates
being up on the five percent range right
and so then you're looking at so you've
got now a third variable you've got the
actual specific characteristics of the
virus that viruses relationship with the
humanity then you've got those two now
in the context of the robustness of the
medical response and here but medical
respond
including all the different
characteristics like the the Chinese
capacity of the government to choose and
then to actively implement quite
draconian quarantine as part of the
medical response right so then I'm going
to know take another step further afield
which we're seeing any wrong and it
seems plausible could see more broadly
which is potentially degradation of the
choice making capacity of the governance
mechanism we have this interesting
character characteristic that this is a
pretty highly viral it spreads quickly
or it can spread broadly and seems to be
a pretty penetrate but the attack rate
meaning that if you're exposed to it the
likelihood that you will catch it is
reasonably high and it
disproportionately impacts people above
certain ages and with certain immune
responses and certain characteristics
which happens to de-identify leadership
in almost every country yes yeah and
projected during an election year when
our current leadership is spending a lot
of time for shaking hands and kissing
babies interacting with each other it
doesn't take much to actually see this
exploding into the leadership yeah in
fact in some sense we might already be
seeing that we might already be in the
leading edge of it which we would then
lead to a potential degradation and
choice-making if you imagine in Iran
that are already showing signs of
government the government is actually
losing its ability to drive effectively
because more and more leadership is
actually off the board off their
capacity to engage in trade cognition
right which creates another feedback
loop and so if you say okay the Chinese
capacity to perceive and choose to make
these draconian quarantines and then to
effectively execute on it is premise not
only on the typology of Chinese
governance in general which we don't
have but also on they the availability
of that governance to propagate down
through the system given the health of
well-being and the understructure
itself so that's the fourth variable and
then another one that's just showing up
I think increasingly and it's
interesting because you know people's
different backgrounds it gives them a
perspective and then if they follow
their perspective and feed it back up
into the larger complex system you can
get this great information
which is pivoting very strongly
initially away from the medical side
into the socio-economic side sure we
were already now beginning to see real
impacts like measurable impacts across a
wide variety of different industries of
the freezing up of the Chinese supply
yeah so the supply chain in China you
know it has been impacted that's
percolated through and even relatively
prosaic institutions like say
restaurants are showing real blockages
in availability of materials also via
Iran my partner's Persian and in Toronto
a lot of the Iranian restaurants are
shutting down because people are coming
back from traveling in Iran and they're
bringing back the virus or the threat of
the virus uh-huh
that whole section of of the Toronto
economy is shutting down I'm actually
gonna actually block that as more of the
demand side but yes that's happening too
so we've got one is the supply side is
percolating up and the others who are
now particularly the first world getting
the demand side which of course the
first one is wouldn't rush the demand
comes from and it's happening across the
board so you know entertainment events
are shutting down canceling big ones
small ones mean the Olympics is probably
going to be nixed South by Southwest is
probably going to be turned off
restaurants particularly you know
restaurants that within the
epistemological sense making tend to be
proximal to danger like Italian
restaurants Persian Chinese but there's
gonna spread more rapidly even Corona
beer hey even crota beer yeah even a
small semantic relationship yeah Travel
is getting completely shut down and of
course that and that and that and that
and that percolates out so if we look at
it edit from the macro level and now
analyses are coming out on this front I
just there's a white paper sitting on my
desktop I haven't went through that came
out of Australia that I think is that's
some good data on this now if you have
you know if I have a healthy person the
immune system is X right in response to
the virus
but now I've got somebody who is a
stressed or has lost their job or can't
pay their rent or can't afford to buy
resources to take care of themselves
then I'm I'm I'm decreasing their
resistance the embedded resistance
sociological level when it increases not
even just the biological resistance
right when you do that you're putting
them into scarcity situations the
cognitive flexibility their ability to
properly rationally direct their own
behavior degenerates as well right
yes yeah so actually no that's another
you say that this is a different factor
that I haven't been able to integrate
into the larger sense which is I've
noticed that there seems to be like
three epistemological positions right
now one is panic one is what I would
call aunty panic and the third is what I
would call carefulness and it's
interesting like I think anti-panic is a
really interesting piece like I hadn't
really thought about it but it's very
commonplace which is to not actually be
careful not to not to make a rational
sort of portfolio allocation of your
choices on the basis of rational spent
risk analysis but actually to choose an
inverted ideological position to panic
and therefore making equally irrational
choices but in the exact opposite
direction I've been personally wrestling
with that so ok so what's you know so I
live with my son and you know you know I
think it's highly probable that we will
get in some sense locked down I think
that's much more probable for example
then we will likely catch a fatal form
of the virus or anything like that so so
you know we're putting aside food and
stuff like that and because of that but
then part of me is part of me is
thinking well like it's a bit of an
inner conflict it's a yes but am I
actually making these evaluations or am
i I'm just running I just being driven
by you know accessibility and
representativeness bias you know cuz I'm
doing all of this but you know getting
in my car is still way more dangerous
and right and you know and I'm still
getting my car every day I'm still going
in the shower which is also right now
more dangerous right and so it's like I
feel you see what I'm saying like
there's a one cell with yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah you saw that but something
comes up so
the way the way that look came to nature
is saying that is it something like the
what's it look like it's like an
equilibrium state in the in RIT between
risk aversion risk seeking and risk new
chapter neutrality in the context of
what you might call low-hanging fruit of
behavioral change yes yes for example
both of us being relatively mature
adults may recall that there has been a
real shift in the relationship between
behavior and getting in your car and
driving over the past five decades yes
yes I recall as a child seeing a car
driving down the road in Texas in the
70s and the person driving it had the
windows rolled down because you couldn't
really run the AC because cars would
blow would overheat with a beer can in
their hand yeah and a cigarette and
their other hand yes which implies
certain that something about how they
were driving I guarantee you no seatbelt
yeah
and so over the past five decades we've
done thing want things like embody as a
basic habit don't drink and drive and
body is a basic habit and I mean whether
it's a habit in the person of the habit
into society enforced by law enforcement
as it Matt like it's a basic habit wear
a seatbelt so there's been some kind of
seeking of social equilibrium of a novel
risk factor automobile that has reached
a point of some something near a saddle
point of these are these are behaviors
that were willing to ingest and and
burden ourselves with in order to seek
something which is kind of the easiest
low-hanging risk mitigation in
relationship to an activity that not
doing it kind of bears too much of a
cost something like that alright so I
get the feeling that but basically what
we're all collectively going through
it's something along those lines in
relationship with the pandemic that has
you know some degree of uncertainty of
the risk so it's like we may find that
like this time next year or this time
two years from now everybody has a box
of you know masks and you know three
months of dried goods in their house
because it's just why not what's at the
end of the day the overall cost burden
is not any different than wearing a seat
belt
during the 99.999 seven
the time that you don't need a seatbelt
right like you know we know if the stars
the stars thing people wearing masks
while traveling in Asia is quite humble
and because it's not that big a deal
once you get over the hump where it
seems odd I get worried I sort of like
who I'm not gonna do things that look
weird once it becomes socially
acceptable alright why not wear a mask
it reduces my risk by n who knows what n
is but the cost is is less than it and
so that I do it I would say with
confidence that that's gonna happen like
there's gonna be a kind of a buildup of
autoimmune like a social level
sociological autoimmune two pandemics
which is actually a medic question which
is actually kind of kind of neat and
useful that's useful because I think I
remember being part of a working group
on biology SF I had like a decade ago
and it wasn't just viruses like memes
and and all kinds of things that spread
using this kind of mathematics but one
of the one of them groups that talked
about it was actual viruses and it was
quite clear at that point they'd given
the the changes in population density
and travel and even animal husbandry
density that novel viruses and bacteria
were going to happen and they were going
to go pandemic there was just no
question that was going to happen
the question is really whenever we're
they're gonna look like yeah this is
sort of an example and hopefully it's a
relatively lightweight example of
something like that and so to the degree
to which we get a nice trial run as a
global civilization of what that looks
like
it gave me building up some good habits
on how to respond which would be great
so that's interesting so that so that's
sort of a more like a long term right
kind of response it's yeah the medical
response there's a cultural shift in
terms of people's background habits that
give an overall increase in adaptivity
to the the risk or the threat yeah yeah
it's like you know folks who grew up on
the gulf coast of mexico tend to have
bottled water and gas generators because
the likelihood of the power going out
due to a big storm is
is high enough that everybody's kind of
culturally aware of it and so the impact
of the power going out in that region is
actually not very high because there's
Brazilians so this this is interesting
because it gives us kind of an indirect
historical method of degree to which a
culture is responsive and sensitive to
its environment so if we could if we
could measure the dissemination of this
habit change we could actually measure
how in tune to you know its environment
a particular culture is so yeah I
imagine there's going to be variations
in this some cultures are going to be
very good at sort of taking this up part
of its gonna be just how how how much
exposure they had right to the virus but
part of its also going to be a measure
of the capacity for a particular culture
to pay attention to you know significant
environmental changes requiring you know
fundamental restructuring in people's
habits yeah yeah and we might even say
also the local structure and the social
structure both maybe that we will see
that there's a certain class of
institutional formations that just
aren't responsive enough that they just
move too slowly or too coarsely and so
that would actually lead to system or
institutional change and then and then
there's obviously things going on oh the
cultural habit habit level yeah yeah and
what was coming to me then it's at the
meta level there is it seems
increasingly likely that in the future
the human future will be one where delta
e is higher than your store appear
usages yes
exactly and so groups or cultures that
are more responsive to a higher rate of
and impact of change will tend to be
more adaptive
I wonder also if people's background
ontology is going to change I mean if
you start changing habits you start
changing habitats what I mean by that if
we get a couple of these in relative
proximity to each other the world is
suddenly going to see a very very
dynamically scary place two people not
that it already wasn't for many people
but it's going to be much more so the
case for them and well that's gonna
challenge a lot of our priming so our
capacity to deny certain aspects of the
environment and did not deny our own
mortality are going to be significantly
changed so I'm thinking here's something
analogous to what the Black Plague did
right really oh yeah really
fundamentally altered social structures
altered people's sense of their
mortality really made them see the world
as much more chaotic there you know it
even later led to a sort of significant
reorientation of our cultural self-image
the will became a much more important
faculty than reason because when the
universe is more chaotic you have to
impose your will much more than reason
finding an order that's already there
that's why you see will based
philosophies and ideologies like the
Nazis emerging in times of significant
weather there's a sense of significant
chaos and threat people oh no no what
really matters is will not reason and
you can even get you can even get anti
rational things emerging and see why I
bring that up is that could also be a
potential feedback mechanism because if
you get that sort of cultural shift
right
that might actually undermine to some
degree the scientific practices we need
to have can we need our science to keep
moving very rapidly because these things
are going to keep shifting and yes
faster actually we need the science to
actually move faster yes and I'm gonna
take it as a fundamental presupposition
that there is an important constitutive
relationship between science the growth
of science
human capacity for being rational and so
if the world becomes scarier and we see
something analogous to what happened in
the Black Plague where we get a shift
towards prioritizing or even the end of
the Vermont Republic we get a shift
towards the prioritization of the will
then and don't let's not forget that at
least North American society seems
particularly vulnerable to that already
right now we have sort of sensitized
people in general to the idea that we
can just assert things and make them so
I think that could feed back and
seriously undermine the science we're
going to need in order to deal with
these viruses did that make sense as an
argument yeah it does it was it was
interesting is that I can't HIPAA thighs
with it I was trying to actually be that
person and I noticed I can't get there
right it's really interesting so yes if
I could try that again well yeah like
it's I think it's historically the case
so you're not denying the history that
I'm referring to
no no no IIIi completely the history's
right I was actually trying to be that
person so I could actually pursue the
inside right right I was trying to
become not see like become somebody for
whom the response to increasing chaos is
a you know triumph of the will
so I mean this did this is chaos right
in the sense like you're talking about
earlier about being overwhelmed right so
it's gonna bring with it a tinge of
horror it's gonna bring the sense that
you know Erickson's idea about sort of
fundamental trust in reality did that
yeah yeah gets eroded in a fundamental
way and you can either what it's gonna
seem to you you have only two options
you can cower or you can fight
mmm-hmm because there's nothing in the
the world that is unfolding in a
predictable manner
it's so you think about the two things
in animals learning experimental
neurosis and learned helplessness
okay so experimental neurosis the
environment becomes unpredictable and
the animal becomes very self-destructive
where are aggressive and bites itself
right or the environment becomes
predictable this is the opposite but it
can't do anything but it becomes too
like depressed right aha
so I'm saying this is going to be much
more like experimental neurosis right
the environments going to be
unpredictable and the people are going
to react to that with a kind of
aggression a kind of yeah so check this
out so it's coming to me the way the way
that showing up is looking very
difficult to process is that it's like
because the rate of change is life could
it be so high and it's a multi-modal you
have the ability to generate a intense
vector and any direction is is
overwhelmed so it's kind of like you
know if I mean inadequately choppy
waters a powerboat doesn't do you any
good
yes it's something like that and so what
ends up happening is it's like this
characteristic of the psycho cultural
dynamic ends up what does it do well it
creates it feels like it just creates
noise like it feels like what ends up
happening is that if somebody goes in
that direction they actually don't so
much create entropy because there's
already so much entropy in the
environment they just disconnect
themselves and basically this is a
version of turning yourself off like you
said it's it's a it becomes a neurosis
where anybody who attaches to that
particular modality welcomes the
increasingly fit so quickly well
I think I'm agreeing with that but I
want to put a bit of a twist on it what
you get is sort of the last-ditch form
of conformity right there's chaos in
within there's chaos without and what
I'll do is I'll just I'll just run with
that conformity right and I'll be I'll
become a vehicle I'll become an
instrument of oh we recorded when I
talked about Panik and anti-panic
I don't remember no yeah yeah I noticed
is that I've noticed in the environment
the milieu there's almost like three
basic positions one disposition is panic
another disposition is anti panic is
what I'm calling it and then third
disposition of something like care in
the context of care there's of course a
whole continuum of ways that people
express and care and that's based upon
their own assessment of the risks and
their own disposition about how they
relate to risk which is you know that's
all kind of what it is but panic and
anti-panic are very different approaches
there these are approaches and seem to
be disconnected from endeavouring to
mate sense that make good choices in the
environment whatever rather commitments
to an ideological or a non rational
irrational relationship with reality so
it sounds like what you're describing is
anti panic is an occasions example of
this sort of thing I yeah maybe yeah
that's a good way of putting it
that you could see the two yeah I think
so
I guess what I what I ended up doing
this was not my intent but I think maybe
we got here is trying to try to get you
try and talk about the way in which this
milieu of complexity gets internalized
into people and then how that actually
shapes and alters the dynamics of the
cognition and that's what that's what
like and their rights if people do not
just have right a manipulative
relationship to their environment they
identify with it and drive identity from
it and so there's an additional threat
that is being posed here and this this
is what sort of starts to lean into the
mean crisis that's what I meant when you
know the people that survived the block
like they didn't die oh right so that
but but they come away from it
internalizing a different world and they
become different kinds of cells it
changes human spirituality in
fundamental ways and so I guess I'm
trying to hear here's where but maybe a
bit of pushback I try to say that the
anti-panic it sounds symptomatic to me
in there with language maybe it's not
and you can correct me if I'm wrong but
I'm trying to point to something that
could be a much more long-term oh yeah
kind of shift oh absolutely I was just
trying to find out like what's uh what
are examples of that long term shifted
maybe already showing up I I think I
think it's when you said that sorry so
when you first made that proposition and
referring to the Black Plague I agree
with you completely
yeah I think this is a the you know way
of putting it in my language is
something like the black plague was to
the Catholic Church what kovat 19 is to
the blue church or something like that
at least with some degree of probability
and you know with box around covered 19
referring to actually Delta II exact
changing environment
the virus is itself symptomatic of more
things that are going to happen right
exactly we're gonna see more and more
things of this abstract kind yeah across
it and more and more diverse versions
right as we're gonna see it coming in
medical we'll see it coming in education
we'll see you know coming and certainly
in politics economics like usually
subsistence is the same topology so
what's interesting is the mind
what's the mind that is associate with
that shift I've spent a lot of time
thinking about the distributed cognition
like that yeah almost the objective
direction which was it look like and how
do people go about doing it but what's
the mind was the interior experience of
what is the nature of reality like I'll
give you an example yep it's been so
long since I've been in this is personal
state I don't actually even remember
what the prior state is like but so this
is just their state a and the state be
okay he is way
it's like Modern Portfolio theory or
sort of like Bayesian statistical
probability where it has not just
fundamental but inescapable mm-hm
and so there is no notion of there being
a true with the capital T there is a
notion there being a cloud of possible
T's and the implications thereof and
you've got this sort of large nest of
things coming through you've got the
actual moment that you're in right now
and they've got a large nest of things
coming out and you just kind of keep
rolling through that so you at any
moment this instantaneous moment is kind
of a collapse of the possibility space
into an actual from which I can change
my sense of what the possibility of the
next moment is going to look like but
I'm always dealing with a probability
manifold sure and therefore my choice
making is very much like a modern
portfolio manager in the financial
system who's basically just allocating
you know risk correlates with each other
yeah and you know that I think that just
massively overlaps with issues around
relevance realization etc etc yeah and
so I feel like my sense is that that's
not commonplace my sense is that there's
a different epistemology which is
something along the lines of
paradigmatic that's okay that that's I
think languaging evidence and the
kuhnian sense yeah okay so I would say
that the paradigmatic mind is a mind
that has a an obligate or near obligate
a high degree of necessity of being of
connecting to one and only one dominant
sense making framework which collapse is
the possibility space enormous I think
it proves the possibility space enormous
and because you don't have any
epistemological uncertainty you only
have uncertainty around the state of
facts that are fitting into your
particular epistemological frame and
that I think is
one of the things that goes away and and
I'm gonna say actually what's
interesting is I'm gonna say that's what
emerged out of the Black Plague was that
kind of Mike the paradigmatic mind yeah
you don't think it exists before the
Black Plague I don't think so or if it
did I think existed very differently you
see if I can unfurl what's why I'm
saying these things
why would I say such a thing so I like
first I wanna make sure I'm
understanding what you mean by
paradigmatic so what you mean by
paradigmatic is a commitment because
there's different readings of Kuhn I
want to make sure I'm not
misunderstanding it yeah yeah so you can
you can read the paradigm as a as a
pragmatic thing or you can read the
paradigm as something that has some sort
of realistic value to it like you know
it's an approximation to the real world
or something like that and then what I
heard you saying was what you meant by
paradigmatic is people have a sense that
there is one true final complete picture
of things and the goal of epistemology
broadly construed is to get to that one
true picture is that the only thing no
no it's more like more like the first
actually nice but the key is that that
it's a almost everybody is it sort of
read only on the paradigm so while there
may be a willingness and at the highest
level philosophy and acceptance of the
premise that the paradigm is the map and
not the territory mm-hm
almost everybody is read only on that
map and almost everybody is actually
unaware of the fact that they're using a
map to enter intermediate the territory
so for practical purposes it shows as
capital T true I see I see which is one
of the reasons why it has such a
hardness like a break like paradigm
shift
to have a collapse vector they tend to
be crack and crumble as opposed to slide
so let me try again then this is helpful
you're saying the paradigm is almost
completely transparent to most people
and that they have sort of no
metacognitive awareness of it in
practice they might have certain sort of
you know abstract statements about you
know paradigms or something like that
but in practice for most people that's
completely transparent yeah okay now I
got you yeah and so there's something so
let's see what was this moustache if
that happens if you take you zoom in on
the on the on the black play and you
ever cut a bunch of different things are
going on simultaneously right you've got
you got the plague you've got exploding
literacy you've got not too long after
you've got to discover the new world
which changes consciousness of
space-time so it's the breakup of the
Catholic world like the true Catholic
world sure in the meaning of the word
Catholic Universal even just the
emergence of Protestantism processes and
the maps to paradigmatic right that
notion of there being a an
acknowledgment of the possibility of a
multiplicity of fundamental models of
what is true
sure and and a distributed cognition how
would I put it method the reorients the
source of true knowledge and that
movement of the source of true knowledge
from the institution the structure to
the individual is that a thing right
let's part of that whole shift towards
the individual will becoming crucial you
you see it and then of course that
reflects back God changes becomes more
will based right and eventually when
even when that God disappears he that
orientation survives and the will to
power of Nietzsche and and things like
that
so you get this long-term fundamental
change so yeah so what's what changing
sounds sounds to me like you're saying
it's a change from some kind of
epistemological monism to a kind of
pluralism and then the response to that
pluralism is sort of the individual will
must impose because the pluralism ZAR
competing with each other is that yeah
yeah there's a bunch of thing so think
about it it's really interesting because
so so in the second mode so that's the
post black death mode we might call just
it in the Enlightenment era one thing is
this for sure is that is the a real loss
of faith in the possibility of a single
fully integrated T mode right so we have
a diversity of different paradigms that
are domain-specific so you know an Isaac
Newton is gonna be holding a paradigm in
relationship to physics and then another
in relationship to religion and probably
another in relationship to politics all
right all right you got a harbor
master's thesis that you get you get
these you get these autonomous spheres
of authority rather than a single
Authority yeah yeah exactly and there's
a mapping issue the mapping happens to
this medium of textual communication so
what ends up happening is the letters
and books flying around create a new
milieu of paradigm coherence and
paradigm editing and modification and in
this notion of like Dewey Decimal
disciplinary structures a lot allow
domain specificity so I can kind of
there may be a completing compatibility
between the evolutionary paradigm and
the physics paradigm but because they're
so far apart of the members of those
groups don't communicate with each other
you don't notice it and then when they
run into each other there's a process of
you know is there an integration between
the two or just kind of ignore them or
what's the relationship and that's kind
of the things a story of the last 500
years has been that kind of thing okay
okay
so I just also by the way I get now your
thesis it's cleared this by the way is
interesting because it relates to an
ambient like if an ambient Delta eat you
know one of the characteristics of the
of the shift from the pre enlightenment
to the Enlightenment ear was in fact a
change in Delta e in along many
different context yes
and so the emergence of that particular
kind of mind paradigmatic in mind in
fact probably is as I'm speaking about
it right now I'm just thinking about it
analogous to the adaptive response that
we're talking about is the transition to
undergoing right now which is there is a
need a fundamental need to transition
from a particular kind of mind that had
huge advantages under certain values of
Delta II but just broke down under
values exceeding Delta II and so we
shifted to this new one and you and you
map out I think very well in lots of
different dimensions the ways that this
new kind of mind tried to get his act
together tried to hang together as I
kept running into a Correa's and
bottlenecks and situations were old
material unraveled and you realize you
were holding on to nothing
mmm so now we're in a context where not
only are we faced with the meaning
crisis in the context of the kind of
them burning out of that model or that
meta model that approach we're also
running into the obsolescence of that
model in the context of a rate of delta
e that is higher than would it could
have handled yes yes yes yeah yeah
that's really nice so check this out I'm
gonna say that again
it's something like
on the one hand in the almost on the
interior of enlightenment mind it has
its own structural instabilities that
kind of as it as it expands and begins
to do its own thing to be itself it
begins to break down and a variety of
ways and and ultimately precede this as
the meaning crisis and all this
different characteristics from the
inside out as a woman and then you flip
it and you say okay and also if we kind
of put ourselves in a place I don't know
like Victorian England 1870 1880 I don't
know would be like peak enlightenment
mind like really functional maybe was
actually like Germany around the time of
the Romantic Romantic movement exactly
sure when we could say pyramid that mind
couldn't possibly have dealt with the
level of delta ii that we're doing with
now no no it's very fundamental nature
just couldn't do this kind of thing so
on them on the left hand side of the
meta-crisis the meaning crisis i guess
the right hand side you've got the
interior meaning that the meaning crisis
is is is showing us that this approach
is in breakdown across the board
reckon on the left hand side you have
the consequence which is that the delta
ii that we are in and are continuing to
to accelerate it overwhelms that
approach even it is best i agree with
that i think that's really important i
think i think that explicate sand
elucidates an intuition i've had for a
very long time which i try to articulate
that there's a deep interconnection
between the meeting crisis and the meta
crisis but now there's some
specification to it i maybe it would be
helpful to think about some of the
interior identity that people had in
sort of that whole enlightenment phase
and how even it see one of the issues is
that you know that interior identity is
still being held onto even though
the meaning crisis is showing that it's
it's collapsing because it's Pro
generating history it has undermined its
its own grammar but that's one thing but
then the other thing is with so that's
that's your pointing back and yes the
pointing forward is ways in which that
is not a vote that you'll allow me these
two terms ways in which that is not only
a degenerative interior identity about
ways in which it's an exacerbating
flirting interior identity it's it's not
only that it's degenerate that it can no
longer but deal with its own history
right it's also you know preventing it's
exacerbating he attempts to it's uh you
know if you allow me a temporal metaphor
it's slowing down the rate of adaptivity
that's needed for the acceleration and
Delta V yes this is this is why I was
saying that these these this paradigm
for example has characteristics of
collapse it has this this thing where it
holds the resources that are necessary
for adaptation in a particular
arrangement and will continue to do so
until enough energy is behind the the
change that needs to be made that that
energy is enough to break this capacity
to hold mm-hmm
yeah this is like a psychotic break yes
yes you have a complete catastrophic
collapse of identity in the face of
something and instead of being able to
make a smooth transition the whole thing
just falls apart
okay so that's great because that now
now we've I think we've began made more
articulate this idea of how the external
chaos actually gets internalized and how
you start to get this resonance between
them yeah yeah so yeah in other we say
that I get the feeling that the
psychosis is probably the right model it
was just to say that we should expect to
see the maladaptive response to the
current environment to be an increase in
the directionality towards psychosis yes
so the defining features of psychosis is
to generally lose a grip on reality
because you see far too many patterns
where there aren't patterns right so
it's it's a decline in the ability to
discern real patterns from merely
correlational patterns so psychotic
people people that are moving towards
psychosis if you give them a screen of
static they they're much more likely to
see or even experience mmm right and so
so they actually feel like it's called
if it's even called a psychotic right
insight they they often feel like
they've had because they do right it's
it's a perversion of the insight
machinery because they suddenly realize
patterns that other people aren't seeing
and that of course gives you right a
tremendous sense that you are now
getting in touch with this chaotic world
well I would say that's actually the
essence of this thing that you were
calling earlier the will right right
right
okay I can't you know it when you're in
a psychotic break your your will yeah
you're going to actually impose your
will in the world is is reduced to your
ability to impose a preferred
meaning-making so the way to feel the
feeling of the head of insight to feel
the feeling of I'm making sense of where
that's all you can get do is you can't
actually affect the world in terms of
really durably over time building a
long-term construct but what you can do
is you can feel like everything makes
sense so would that mean then what we
should see if this line of argument is
going the right way is that we should
see an increase in people creating over
our drive to great overarching fantastic
in the pejorative sense of the word
fantastic like meta-narratives like
grand conspiracy theories yes absolutely
absolutely yeah because you're gonna
have two things happening simultaneously
one is they're going to be taking the
red pill they're gonna exit the existing
dominant sense making and media making
architectures that are clearly black
stop feeling all around them yeah
they're gonna dive into the deep end
about a Delta II that is way beyond
their capacity to make sense of it and
and either oh it's nice didn't usually
really either get a learned helplessness
I kind of get a shutdown overwhelmed
yeah or you're gonna get the equivalent
of a neurotic you know in this case it's
a psychotic break right right right
exactly yeah luckily yeah yeah so the
question and you're gonna feel empowered
for both of those alternatives because
the tradition right is right has
basically let you down yes very very
profound ways oh absolutely in fact it's
the only thing you can really hold on to
for sure that the tradition it doesn't
work yes yes it's almost like your your
spirit you you know how to steer away
from something the question is what are
you steering towards right right so
let's let's do this I mean I want to
pivot all the way back to the outside
coming back in sure but consciously not
at a meta level using that to inform
this conversation because I think
there's something very powerful here
cool so one of the things that I was
contemplating this morning is I was
running a an integration pass is that it
actually feels like there's a very
strong bifurcation in terms of the the
impact of kovat 19 Mon us right right
though so I'm gonna push a button and
I'm gonna do a flash collapse of my
Bayesian net and just take a couple of
assumptions please so the highest
probability models that I've seen have
something like the and the ambient
mortality rate is something on the order
of an average of about five percent
meaning they're just sort of introduced
us to wild-type humans you'd have a
fifteen to twenty percent mortality
above eighty and kind of casting you
know curves down and so cross total
populations skewing higher for men you
get kind of that rate and then in a
well-managed high-quality medical
environment it's sort of below point two
so that's kind of the spread that you're
dealing with it's a huge variation huge
variation and what's interesting is that
that variation feeds back on itself so
to the degree to which your choice
making your social choice making make
sense of the risk and then make choices
to
maintained the resilience and integrity
of your choice making and action taking
capacity particularly the subdomain of
of your medical system and your agentive
capacity is equal to the vector of the
harm that you're dealing with then
you're actually able to hold the entire
system dynamics in this left-hand path
and keep it at below point two and then
it burns out I so more or less the story
of China as far as we can tell and you
have this thing the tidal wave was
building right it's got this exponential
build curve you see it coming you
respond quickly enough and you've got
enough embedded resilience at the
medical level that your medical system
can take it absorb the energy of what's
coming at you not get overwhelmed hold
hold hold and then it ships that now
right so that's kind of path one and
what's interesting about path one is
that it has a bunch of self-reinforcing
feedback loops is that once you begin to
see that it's working what gets what
works gets more cycles pointed to it you
begin to realize what the thing you're
dealing with looks like there's a whole
bunch of stuff on path one then passed
to what happens is you know you wait too
long or you act too slowly or you ask
with not enough resilience or impact and
you start getting to a point of
overwhelm and you get overwhelmed let's
say the medical level that you don't
have enough hospital beds you have
enough ventilators you don't have enough
spent antivirals you don't have enough
hospital staff you don't move hospital
staff correctly you know wherever it
weakens the immune system of your social
environment as you start seeing that
mortality rate going ah because you're
starting to get outside of the zone of a
controlled situation and and by the way
also not just not just a mortality rate
but but even more importantly in the
initial stages the virality rate your
quarantine structures aren't strong
enough and you're just trying to get
more and more you're fighting a fire
that's growing faster than your
responsive capacity and so once once the
fire gets past a certain threshold in
its relationship with your responsive
capacity you start getting a separation
because it's degrading your responsive
capacity ya know you're dealing with
something where you're depleting your
medical resources you're beginning to
lose like we've actually seen now people
inside biopharma so
in the biopharma industry are certain to
show up as being infected
which means smart people that would
otherwise be working in Diagnostics or
antivirals are actually being taken off
the board and their teams are degraded
in functionality so you've got a
degradation in functionality as I talked
about earlier you've got the degradation
of functionality portable of leadership
you run as a situation where their
ability to make choices is going down
because more and more choice makers are
starting to music get sick right and so
this becomes the right-hand path source
to have these feedback loops where
there's a bifurcation event pivoting
around basically your your overall auto
immune system as a society and the
rising meta systemic dynamics of the
vector and there's a breaking point a
bifurcation event that takes you here or
it takes you here right and of course
there's there's things in between which
is to say you know how hard is the tide
go in before you catch it and bring it
down you know China in Wuhan Wuhan
looked a lot like the right hand path
left to its own devices if Wuhan was by
itself it would been on the right hand
path like it would have been they would
have been melt up there's no there was
no benefit because mulan was in the
context of china as a larger context
this systemic resilience of all of China
it got hit by Wuhan but was able to not
break as a total system and therefore
was able to push the whole of China back
down to the left-hand path okay
so what's interesting about this is this
so much of this actually pivots on
choice making so much as pivots at
associate and distributed cognitive
cognitive level on our ability to make
sense of what's happening clearly and
rapidly and they make effective choices
in a timely fashion and with the right
amount of impact to actually respond to
what's happening but before we're
overwhelmed by an exponentially growing
curve I feel like that that that notion
that insight of choice making response
all the way back to the conversation
were just having her so I don't know I
just actually recalling all that evil is
give me a mind what we were just talking
about I just thought we were talking
about the fact that people you know
internalized the environment and the kit
and we were sort of there's a
possibility that what people will do
will
they have something sort of analogous to
a psychotic reaction to ice also noise
and and you know and this is an aspect
you said this is a way of understanding
this notion of will right there finding
meaning and and you know the possibility
that what we'll see is that you know the
rapid possibly exponential growth of
conspiracy theories and all kinds of
things that divert resources and
problem-solving abilities and
distributed cognition and distributed
labor okay
ways that could be really exhaustive
eight things yeah okay so then so remap
some of these notions so there's a
mapping here of something like should be
part of distribute cognition
he says act okay that's it that's the
key this is the important thing the
human beings are obligate tribal okay so
we are we are part of something yes and
so for if we're not part of something we
are drift yes and what's happening is is
that whereas we as you as you exit is
you take the red plate as you exit the
the tradition that is not working you
you now are adrift and and to the degree
to which you're able to find something
that you can be part of that is itself
has the at least the ingredients to be
adapted it may actually not initially be
adapted but it has the annuity has the
capacity has the scope and competence to
actually be able to start making
effective choices in the context of
what's happening you will naturally
begin to up gradient in that direction
so okay how's that show up hmm I had
like all right right sure to check it
out
where was this something happens
somewhere where there was a crisis there
was a town and in the town you had a
political structure and oh it was during
Katrina so Mississippi Katrina right the
you know hurricane his the leaders are
breaking and the existing political
structure just drops them all right
right what happens is this one guy who's
like the guy who runs the general store
has his shit together and he starts to
coordinate coordinate effective choices
we're talking about local small-scale
effective choices but that creates an
attractor and of
people who swiftness that attractor
they're like looking and they're seeing
chaos in all directions and they see one
spot over there there's not chaos in all
directions and they begin to orient
themselves towards that and so he says
okay well you do this and they start
doing that and as it turns out that
doesn't fuck that doesn't suck it works
a little bit and and by the way been
working with him it works better so then
the zone of coordinated action the zone
of order the zone of non chaos begins to
grow organically because we were that
obligate tribalism is that if we don't
as individuals looner lose our capacity
as individuals to see and orient towards
what is truly effective choice in our
context as long as we have that capacity
which is our natural human mobility and
then we have the capacity to orient
ourselves to it in a flexible way so
that we can upgrade Ian its capacity
then you get a positive feedback loop in
the environment that you're in so it's
that liminal shamanic um we're dealing
with chaos all the time really and so
let's actually use that skill set to
Rico here something that is leaps all
over it you know crosses the chasm you
know does the valley crossing into
something that works right yeah this
feels like this is a little bit of a
prophecy I mean I think what we're about
to witness is that I think we're about
to witness in the West is a generalised
failure of traditions institutional
structures leadership as it currently
exists for reasons both of corruption
and ontological epistemological
inadequacy right and the movement
towards the collective intelligence to
move it towards distributed intelligence
cognition binding those individuals and
groups that are actually able to make
increasingly effective choices in the
context of what's really happening and
then learning how to Rico here and we
coordinate with those groups so that
they were able to scale and increase
their effectiveness I would say is if
not this time and I think this time is a
good opportunity like it's a good trial
run and it may be the one where that
happens if not this time it will be sort
of in the next few times of this you
know this increase in Delta II mmm-hmm
human Yoko Sargon but there is a problem
I see in that I mean that your prophecy
I think your prophecy is accurate what I
meant is cuz now I'm thinking again of
other example if I'm a republic ah it
you get an int you get a group of
individuals who are locally very
effective but it turns out that the
global solution that they're proposing
is actually while it ends up destroying
Germany right it actually turns out to
be massively self-destructive yeah the
the so you clearly have individuals that
on the on the street right and in in you
know in the marketplace of Germany like
they're they're they're they're creating
that attractor of order that's well
that's why they succeed right there but
what they do is that that particular
configuration the dynamical system they
engendered I mean this is kind of you
know a version of the tragedy of the
Commons right it's locally order
generating but what it it's it's in the
service again of this growth of a
psychotic conspiracy theory that
ultimately puts the whole you know the
whole country on a path of
self-destruction yeah I think well I
think what we're gonna see is we're
gonna see something like a million Nazi
parties oh right I think I think we're
gonna see is just lots and lots and lots
of micro psychotic cabal's yes
and the question is going to be how do
they relate to each other because the
level of systemic breakdown is is you
know the default state is failure so
it's not like we need Nazis to fail it's
more like we need something we need to
sort of the opposite of Nazis to succeed
and the default state is failure right
so what does that look like well it
looks a little bit like what Peter
cultural r2 dot oh yeah yeah but but x
yeah multiplied by a factor probably
five orders of magnitude oh yeah so my
concern there is then you you get you
get general systems collapse because if
you get this proliferation falls the
your internal social environment becomes
as complex and unmanned
as unmanageable as the external
environment you're trying to respond to
wow you know it's interesting in this
case like something like a virus and
here specifically nature may be our
saving grace hmm
because if the if the if the complexity
is happening higher in the human social
stack so no politics finance it's like
sociology things like identity and
mimetics culture those are so easily I
read this the next or amenable to
psychosis mmm-hmm
as long as I can tell a locally
effective story that kind of makes me
feel like I'm making sense of my
environment hiking I can kind of go
forward until I bump into something
nature doesn't give a fuck if my story
is that it's funny I think it just
happened actually in Iran a cleric you
went to go admitted Minister some people
who have got the virus and he didn't
take any precautions because his his his
model was that he would be protected and
he got sick and died this isn't clear
what your psychotic story is like
that'sthat's rock-bottom
instead I kind of break it hits rock
bottom and so you know not being sick or
not dying from sickness is like the kind
that's look that that's it wow I forgot
about that
just a cute to check some of this whole
story is is nature now the end of the
day we're all running psychotic
narratives the questions are they
adaptive psychotic narratives or not
right right so the more the crisis is
that we run into our non sociological
crises to protect natural actual natural
crises that are missed sorrel so you
know climate change unfortunately until
it is so intense that it's irrelevant
it's not visceral now you kind of
everything you're seeing is mediated by
a very large interpretive distance and
so you can always run a narrative in
between those two points yes and avoid
avoid
rock-bottom yeah in to hit you in the
face with something that you can't avoid
no matter what there was something like
getting sick and dying from a virus
that's growing very rapidly you know if
you take a look at it every one of these
micro cabal's of psycho psychotics
they're gonna get sick if this is real
like this is or there's a real thing
where specifically their local
adaptiveness will be somewhat obviously
less than others now what you're about
to say I think it's certainly up into my
mind is they you know hardcore prepper
communities are going to be
indistinguishable from groups are
actually making effective choices you
know in a larger context like there's a
whole bunch of nodes uh-huh there's
whole bunch of solutions to this
particular event that are probably
equivalent in terms of their
adaptiveness unless the event is really
big right and so it's weird like it's
one of these things where I'm noticing
as I'm talking like wow it would
actually maybe be best for us if this is
a bigger thing then it seems like it
might be because it would be a enough
felt reality that it would push our
consciousness past certain black holes
that were in right now so more like the
Bronze Age collapse yeah which article
right you get this PC ation of all these
noose you know cultural economic
political forms of organization and
cognition changes fundamentally yeah in
fact if you think about it like if you
think okay so we can go up you can say
the Chinese went through that kind of
dynamic what seven times like every
every dynasty has gone through a
collapse that was on the order of like
two-thirds mortality right in a couple
hundred years of chaos and then that
gave rise to the next dynasty it's funny
because the continuity of China which is
different than the discontinuity of the
Bronze Age I think is precisely that
more term attitude though is we've got
some sixty percent to seventy five
percent or something like that you
probably have no longer China to China
you have something which is you know the
Hittites
to the Greeks yeah and then on the so
then you've got like the Bronze Age
collapse
the Chinese collapse the Roman collapse
and then like the Black Plague something
like that or the Black Plague awful as
it was didn't really interrupt the
continuity of the West
it created a real the thing that came
out the other end was very very
different but I would say and deeply
fundamentally was still still thought of
itself as the West at least yeah yeah
there's a continuity of I there's a
certain continuity of identity back
beyond it yes I guess yeah so this is do
the map all the way back down to the
individual so if you've got somebody
who's it got you know delusion or an
addiction there's there's how hard do
you have to hit rock bottom to have your
moment of clarity and that's the
question and ideally you don't have to
hit too hard the softer you can hit it's
the moment of clarity you're looking for
it's not the rock-bottom you're looking
for yeah yeah and I guess that's the
question is how hard do we have to hit
rock bottom to have an ammo Monteux
clarity adequate to the amount of change
that we need to make in our interior and
our exterior to be truly adaptive to the
context that we're finding ourselves in
that's a good question that's a good
question
so I mean it's something that comes up
into a mind it's not a direct logical
following from this but what we've just
said but I was like I'm seeing this
picture now of groups of people who like
do the basically do the learned
helplessness and they just try to escape
mm-hmm right and then we have the the
proliferation of the cabal's
which is is kind of like the
experimental psychosis right and they're
right but but there seems to be and so I
get that I think that's good there seems
to be in another psychological dimension
that's at work here and I don't know how
it fits in here but I thought about it
when you were mentioning something and I
want to be really carefully because I
don't know if I miss it miss attributing
so grain of salt on this but remember
you're talking about how the the the the
thing about climate change is you've got
this displacement right this
displacement issue that
people to defer right they so basically
they have deferral strategies of denying
or right or mitigating or reducing
response because it's displaced right
and I again this is looks right now it's
anecdotal I don't have any data nobody
would have to hear on this yet but it it
seems to me that there's a I don't want
to call it pleasure but there's
something about this being concrete and
present that is alleviating for people
that it takes the miasma of the meaning
crisis and puts a concrete agent face on
it that we ask few things about and
right and so part I want to be really
cautious here and I know you you know
you respect that but part of the part of
the reason why I think also you're
getting the panic well this is this is
an ideal idea that goes back to Tillich
and from one of the things people do
with anxiety is they try to transmute it
into fear because if they can transmute
anxiety into fear then they can do
something as opposed to just have that
of ambiguity and man that is an intense
notion mmm-hmm one of the things that
people do with anxiety is they
transmuted into fear Wow and it's the
in-depth and and that could that kind of
feeds into the conspiracy generation
because what conspiracies do as
psychological adaptive mechanisms is
they translate existential anxiety into
actionable fear because now there's the
threat whatever as the Cabal which which
how it works however overwhelming is at
least concrete enough that in principle
agency is possible so you know I
sometimes call this the demonization
strategy one of the ways you know it I
sometimes say to people I mean this sort
of how ironically it would be kind of
wonderful if there was a devil it would
be wonderful if all of the evil and
suffering actually had you know an
orchestrated genius behind it because
then at last we could know what it is
we're supposed to do
yeah very clearly we've turned it from
an ill-defined problem into a
well-defined problem it's a hard problem
but you know what it's not anymore it's
not an ill-defined problem right so how
do you know you're not in the Cabal yeah
how do we how do we go about as
individuals navigate these chalk
navigating these choppy waters well I'm
wondering if that's I'm wondering if
that's one of the things I mean so a few
minutes ago you're talking about a kind
of wisdom we need in order to write sure
we're going down the left-hand as you as
you put it I'm suggesting to you that
part of that wisdom might be the kind of
self knowledge of this modal kind of
self-deception and one of the so if I'm
aware that I'm doing a lot of shifting
of anxiety interfered that from me is a
red flag that forget what flag I love it
right a red flag that I'm probably
getting into conspiratorial Kabbalistic
gnostic in the pejorative sense of the
word kind of thinking right yes
absolutely
it's really interesting I'm loving the
the inverse where the Black Plague broke
the religion that was a religion yeah
and this this new thing is is what gives
rise to the religion that's not a
religion you just you just described one
you know one piece one one wouldn't you
is it a college homily no a reading
right or reading a reading from the book
of the religion that's not a religion
chapter 7 verse 3 if you notice that
you're shifting anxiety into fear then
it's a red flag yeah that's a red flag
and then the converse would be not just
teaching people amelioration of anxiety
that's a good you need something more
like what we saw happen after the Black
Plague week you again the the
identification of your interior life
it's fun the grammar of that has
fundamentally changed it would have to
be something more like in that there are
more deep so deeper into the guts of the
psyche
response to uncertainty and dynamic
change is something other than anxiety
and we all but it has to be well no no
we've reconfigured the grammar before we
have done this multiple times so so one
is you know first of all perhaps the
first step is well am i translating
anxiety into fear right well that's bad
but another one is can I get deeper than
the response of anxiety and come up with
something other than anxiety as a
response to uncertainty oh it's so good
isn't it I mean it's funny like this
it's like it's like going through the
looking glass because what you're
talking about is faith
a kind of faith yes it's a become that
we had talked about we've talked about
the several times we've come to be a
same place many times right yeah it's
not an ideological it's not an
irrational commitment to an ideology
it's not a willful assertion of a
proposition it's a cultivated sense of
being uh like having a participatory
conformity with an ongoing
transformative process in reality it's
continuity of contact rather than
closure into conclusion right boys
that's a bunch of good words man so
there's a ten time stamp whatever this
is right now that was uh that was it
somebody write that down in the comments
yeah the the visual image I have is of
like a buoy in the ocean that has you
know it just it's weighted such that
even as the water I was having a sailing
imagery the person who can sort of can
ride the edge of the storm a family
right yeah it's you don't want to get
swamped right that's the key yeah and so
you know having a series of capacities
and abilities including the ability to
just sort of like surrender to what's
happening so that you're not breaking as
the system pushes on you but you're
actually able to just keep that that all
always stay in continuity of contact
yeah always stay there because you know
that if you're out of there you're in
trouble
and if you're in there you can at least
recover all right the penny if you if
the wave if the winds died down a little
bit you're back into the salient yep
yeah that's that's the key yeah that's
cool
that's really cool there's a story by
Joseph Conrad about a ship that gets
swamped and the sailors are all Stan
are sort of holding onto the side of the
ship it's actually been swamped and and
Alliston the captain
he's just they're all watching him good
they have a they have a kind of they
have a faith in him but he's watching
and he's watching and he's watching and
then all of a sudden goes okay now raise
that sail that sail that sail and then
he goes right timing of wind and wave
and the shipwrights there you go
so he like he represents exactly that
buoy right he was young he was aware
that he even being swamped is not being
swamped yes yes yeah all in all it
seemed like all was lost but as long as
the captain has got their eye on the
wind you know that you have a chance and
they knew long as he had his eye on the
winds that they had a chance and so they
stayed together in pop and that's that's
it that's a great story yeah hmm yeah so
that's it's funny cuz so he didn't do is
he didn't lose faith
he didn't mean he didn't fall and to
learned helplessness or neuroses and he
stated he wasn't just doing willful
assertion he's not a Rambo hero right
that's the point
he's not a Rambo hero and he doesn't
just all I will you know he doesn't just
sort of muscle or force his way through
it's it's like the Wu way of Taoism
right he he fine he looks for the grain
and he have sensitivity to find the
grain and align himself with it so that
he gets that timing and it's just like
that yeah good I got to go soon anyways
my friend I would like to pick this up
again and maybe we could pick it up with
a conversation in depth
maybe link the two things back together
the religion that's not a religion and
this we are getting pieces of what this
me formulation of faith needs yeah yeah
I think it's powerful yeah and I think
we should start there and then try and
build on that what do you think a
breakup is a proposal I love it so is
this call so we were we were supposed to
have called Wednesday yeah we know we're
doing now so on our current schedule
we're not gonna have another
conversation for another 10 days is that
right that's right okay I'm happy to
change that
okay flexible yeah I'll take a look at
my calendar and maybe we could we could
get another time in this I feel the iron
is hot right now and it would be good to
strike it with good timing and pace with
I'll talk to you soon take care thank
you very much
excellent excellent conversation very
timely mm-hmm